Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project 194
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 2: 2015-2016 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2015-2016
    - Shirley Debrow interview, 2016-01-02; rwhc_ohp_2015_011.wav; Debrow, Shirley, 1946-; Debrow, Samuel
      In this oral history interview, Ms. Shirley Debrow discusses her life and experiences moving from North Carolina to Washington, DC. Ms. Debrow discusses her early life in the South, her move to Philadelphia in 1964, and her move to Washington, DC, in 1966. Ms. Debrow also talks about her life in Washington, her career at the DC Department of Parks and Recreation, and her love of travel.
      Migration, Internal; African Americans; Black persons; Women
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2015-2016
    - Bernard Hayes index, 2015-12-18; rwhc_ohp_2015_009_ind.pdf; Hayes, H. Bernard, 1953-; Hassan, Ahmad
    - Caesar Dudley index, 2015-12-18; Dudley, Caesar, -2018; Bayliss, Michael
    - Damita Jo Goldsmith index, 2016-02-01; Goldsmith, Damita Jo, 1951-; Akhigbe, Rebecca
    - Eleanor Kelly index, 2015-12-01; Kelly, Eleanor; Branch, Maya
    - Henry Breedlove index, 2016-01-01; Breedlove, Henry, 1939-; Jones, Mattie
    - Julius Watson index, 2016-04-06; Watson, Julius; Thomas, Isaiah
    - Kathy Elaine Senior index, 2016-01-16; Senior, Kathy Elaine, 1941-; Yadeto, Jabesso
    - Korea Strowder index, 2015-12; Strowder, Korea Clark, 1920-2018; Rich, Jamilya
    - Louise Baxter index, 2016-01-07; Baxter, Louise; Aguilar, Kenya
    - Mabel Mitchell index, 2016-01-08; rwhc_ohp_2015_010_ind.pdf; Mitchell, Mabel; Eigsti, Allison
    - Shirley Debrow index, 2016-01-02; rwhc_ohp_2015_011_ind.pdf; Debrow, Shirley, 1946-; Debrow, Samuel
      In this oral history interview, Ms. Shirley Debrow discusses her life and experiences moving from North Carolina to Washington, DC. Ms. Debrow discusses her early life in the South, her move to Philadelphia in 1964, and her move to Washington, DC, in 1966. Ms. Debrow also talks about her life in Washington, her career at the DC Department of Parks and Recreation, and her love of travel. Born in 1946, Shirley M. Debrow grew up in North Carolina w
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2015-2016
    - Bernard Hayes transcript, 2015-12-18; rwhc_ohp_2015_009_tra.pdf; Hayes, H. Bernard, 1953-; Hassan, Ahmad
    - Caesar Dudley transcript, 2015-12-18; Dudley, Caesar, -2018; Bayliss, Michael
    - Damita Jo Goldsmith transcript, 2016-02-01; Goldsmith, Damita Jo, 1951-; Akhigbe, Rebecca
    - Eleanor Kelly transcript, 2015-12-01; Kelly, Eleanor; Branch, Maya
    - Henry Breedlove transcript, 2016-01-01; Breedlove, Henry, 1939-; Jones, Mattie
    - Julius Watson transcript, 2016-04-06; Watson, Julius; Thomas, Isaiah
    - Kathy Elaine Senior transcript, 2016-01-16; Senior, Kathy Elaine, 1941-; Yadeto, Jabesso
    - Korea Strowder transcript, 2015-12; Strowder, Korea Clark, 1920-2018; Rich, Jamilya
    - Louise Baxter transcript, 2016-01-07; Baxter, Louise; Aguilar, Kenya
    - Mabel Mitchell transcript, 2016-01-08; rwhc_ohp_2015_010_tra.pdf; Mitchell, Mabel; Eigsti, Allison
    - Shirley Debrow transcript, 2016-01-02; rwhc_ohp_2015_011_tra.pdf; Debrow, Shirley, 1946-; Debrow, Samuel
- Series 3: 2016-2017 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2016
    - Alberta Bryant interview, 2016-12-01; rwhc_ohp_2016_002.wav; Bryant, Alberta, 1929-; Marks, Harris
      Ms. Alberta Bryant was born in New York City in 1929 but spent her summers visiting her mother's family in Charleston, South Carolina throughout her upbringing. When Ms. Bryant was 13 years old, her mother passed away and she moved in with an aunt and uncle. After graduating from high school, Ms. Bryant worked as a registrar for the New York City Board of Education for a short time. She then attended the Harlem Hospital School of Nursing and became a registered nurse. Shortly after marrying her husband, a Washingtonian, Ms. Bryant moved to Washington, D.C., in 1953. In Washington, she worked at the District of Columbia General Hospital, ultimately retiring in the mid-eighties at age 55. Ms. Bryant is a member of Mount Jezreel Baptist Church in Silver Spring, Maryland, and is a mother, grandmother, and great-grandmother.
      In this oral history interview, Ms. Alberta Bryant, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences growing up in New York City, visiting Charleston, South Carolina, throughout her youth, and moving to Washington, D.C., in 1953, after marrying her husband. The interview later turns into a discussion of contemporary issues of race and class that shifts into a conversation about the political situation at the time of the interview. This section touches upon issues such as misinformation, partisanship, and the 2016 election.
      Segregation; Racism; Nurses; Civil rights movement
    - Willie Williams interview, 2016-11-27; Williams, Willie; Jefferson, Trenni
      Willie Williams was born in the 1940s in Tarboro, North Carolina. Despite living in the country, he attended school in Tarboro and was working in upstate New York during the summers by the time he was in high school. After graduating from high school in 1962, Mr. Williams attended college at Fayetteville University for a time before moving to D.C. at the suggestion of a friend. When Mr. Williams first came to the District, he lived with his uncle in Fairfax Village in far Southeast. After working for a couple years, Mr. Williams joined the Army. After leaving the Army in 1969, Mr. Williams and his wife moved back to Washington and lived near 28th Street and Pennsylvania Avenue SE. He worked at the United States Postal Service for a several years before taking advantage of the G.I. Bill and enrolling at Federal City College (now UDC). After four or five years of part-time enrollment he graduated in 1977 with a degree in business education. Mr. Williams then attempted to become a CPA but ultimately didn't complete his certification, and he went on to work a variety teaching positions (teaching accounting for the National Park and Planning Commission in Maryland, teaching typing at Cortez Peters Business College, and substitute teaching in D.C. Public Schools) before becoming a realtor. Mr. Williams remained in Washington after his retirement in 1992, but some time after 2016, he moved to Kennesaw, Georgia.
      In this oral history interview, Willie Williams, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his life and experiences moving from Tarboro, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. Mr. Williams discusses his upbringing in Tarboro, a period of time he and his family lived in Virginia, his time at Fayetteville State University as well as student activism in Fayetteville, and his decision to move to Washington in 1964. He also talks about his experience in the Army and his return to D.C. after leaving the service in 1969, using the G.I. Bill to attend Federal City College (UDC) in the 1970s, his son's schooling in Washington, and how he met his wife.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2016
    - Alberta Bryant index, 2016-12-01; rwhc_ohp_2016_002_ind.pdf; Bryant, Alberta, 1929-; Marks, Harris
      Bibliography
    - Willie Williams index, 2016-11-27; Williams, Willie; Jefferson, Trenni
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2016
    - Alberta Bryant transcript, 2016-12-01; rwhc_ohp_2016_002_tra.pdf; Bryant, Alberta, 1929-; Marks, Harris
    - Willie Williams transcript, 2016-11-27; Williams, Willie; Jefferson, Trenni
- Series 4: 2017-2018 School Year
  - Sub-series 1: Interviews, 2017
    - Herbert Freeman interview, 2018-01-04; rwhc_ohp_2017_005.wav; Freeman, Herbert, 1941-; Okbagabir, Hadnet
      Herbert Freeman was born on May 3, 1941, in Vanceboro, North Carolina. When Mr. Freeman was two years old his father became ill, and his mother moved him and his siblings to Engelhard, NC. In Engelhard Mr. Freeman's mother worked as a domestic worker and raised her six children by herself. Mr. Freeman attended school through twelfth grade in Engelhard and worked in tobacco during his youth. He later worked at a segregated white-only beach in Nags Head, NC. Though Mr. Freeman first came to Washington in 1962, he soon returned to North Carolina to attend a barber school. After he completed school, Mr. Freeman returned to DC, earned his barbering license, and began working as a barber in Washington. After working at several different barber shops, Mr. Freeman opened his own barber shop in Brightwood Park in 1976, Freeman's House of Styles. Mr. Freeman has been married for over fifty years, has two sons, and continues to work at his barber shop to this day.
      In this oral history interview, Mr. Herbert Freeman, owner of Freeman's House of Styles in Brightwood Park, discusses his life and experiences moving from Engelhard, North Carolina, to Washington, DC. Mr. Freeman discusses his early life in Engelhard, his move to Washington, DC, in 1962, his transition to life in the city, and his long and successful career as a barber in Washington. He also discusses violence against Black people in both the past and present, segregation in North Carolina, and the 1968 Riots in Washington, DC after the assassination of Martin Luther King.
      Black persons; Migration, Internal; African Americans
    - Jettie Brown interview, 2017-12-24; rwhc_ohp_2017_004.wav; Brown, Jettie M., 1930-
      Mrs. Jettie Brown was born on September 23, 1930, in Blair, Virginia, and grew up with her mother, father, and seven siblings. The family lived and worked on a farm as sharecroppers in Blair, but they migrated to Chester, Pennsylvania, after an incident in which Mrs. Brown's father was cheated at settlement by his employer. In Chester, Mrs. Brown met and married her husband, Rev. Ulysses Brown, and the two moved to Long Island, New York. Mrs. Brown got a job working for AT and T and was able to continue her education in Long Island, receiving a bachelor's degree in Christian Education. After her husband's retirement Mrs. Brown and her husband moved to Washington, D.C, and she has worked as substitute teacher since arriving in the District. Mrs. Brown also serves on the Mothers' Board of Greater Refuge Temple of Washington, D.C, and is currently taking classes at Liberty University.
      In this oral history interview, Jettie Brown discusses her life and experiences moving from Blair, Virginia, to Chester, Pennsylvania, to Long Island, New York, and ultimately to Washington, D.C. Mrs. Brown talks about her upbringing and family life on the farm in Blair, segregation and race relations in Blair, and her family's migration to Chester, Pennsylvania, when she was twenty years old. Mrs. Brown also discusses moving to Long Island with her husband and their move to the Washington, D.C., area.
      Black persons; Migration, Internal; African Americans; Women
    - Jimmie Suggs interview, 2017-12-11; Suggs, Jimmie, 1952-; Woods-Arthur, Maya
      Jimmie Suggs was born in 1952 in Stantonsburg, North Carolina, and has three brothers and three sisters. Mr. Suggs grew up working in tobacco fields, picking cotton and corn, and securing odd jobs around town. He also was a serious athlete (softball and basketball) and has continued playing sports throughout his life. He attended Speights High School in Saratoga, North Carolina, before integrating Lee Woodard High School in Black Creek, North Carolina, in his junior year. Mr. Suggs' basketball coach from Speights drove him to and from Lee Woodard every day since he had gotten a job as assistant principal there. The same year he enrolled at Lee Woodard, 1969, Mr. Suggs began coming to D.C. for summer work. One of Mr. Suggs' older brothers had moved to D.C. in 1966, and his mother had been encouraging him to do the same since there was little economic opportunity in their area. Upon graduating from high school, he moved to Washington for good. Mr. Suggs has worked a variety of jobs throughout the D.C. region including work as a Metrobus driver, truck driver, locksmith, construction worker, and mechanic/garage attendant.
      In this oral history interview, Jimmie Suggs, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Stantonsburg, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. He discusses coming up as a "southern boy," being the first Black student to integrate the local public high school, the expectations of his household, and never losing his Southern identity after moving to D.C. He also discusses changes he's witnessed in the city.
    - Reverend Dr. Isaac Fox interview, 2017-12-19; Fox, Isaac A.; Messina-Fitzgerald, Clare
      In this oral history interview, the Reverend Dr. Isaac Fox, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Nashville, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. He recalls his upbringing and education in Nashville, his move to D.C. in 1953, and his experiences serving in the U.S. Military. Rev. Fox also discusses his varied educational experiences and his lifelong dedication to education.
      Rev. Dr. Isaac Fox was born in the 1930s in Nashville, NC, and was one of Susie and Ned Will Fox's eleven children. He attended school in Nashville until the ninth grade at which point he decided to drop out and pursue a musical career singing in a quartet. After deciding he wasn't making enough money singing, Rev. Fox came to Washington in 1953 and stayed with an older cousin in the District. After a year living in D.C., he was drafted into the service and served overseas. Rev. Fox completed a GED while in France, and upon returning to the U.S., returned to North Carolina to complete his high school requirements. Rev. Fox then received a BS in Chemistry from Shaw University in Raleigh, NC, in 1962. While attending Shaw, he met his wife and the two married in 1960. They went on to have two daughters. Rev. Fox worked as a chemist at NIH, and continued to receive further education throughout his life (M.S. in Science Teaching from American University, M.S. in Information Science from UD.C., M.Div. from Howard University School of Divinity, and ultimately received a Doctor of Divinity and Doctor of Ministry from the Esoteric Theological Seminary in 2011). Rev. Fox has been involved with Vermont Avenue Baptist Church since 1997 and served in a variety of roles including interim pastor from 2016 - 2018.
    - Sarah Ann Hardy interview, 2017-12-26; Hardy, Sarah Ann, 1947-; Wilson, Ramani
      Sarah Ann Hardy was born in Randleman, North Carolina, in 1947. She grew up with her mother, father, and four siblings: one sister and three brothers. Her father was sharecropper and brick mason, who built homes, and her mother was a domestic worker. Though Ms. Hardy attended segregated schools in Randleman, schools were integrated after she graduated from high school in 1965 and her younger siblings attended the newly integrated white school. After graduating, Ms. Hardy enrolled in Southeastern Business College but soon returned home and enrolled at North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University, which she attended from 1965-1966. In 1966, at age 19, Ms. Hardy was visited her cousin in Washington, D.C., and enjoyed her visit so much that she decided not to return home. She quickly found work in the federal government and worked within the same agency for 42 years. In 2008, at age 61, Ms. Hardy retired from her job and moved back to North Carolina to tend to her mother who had taken ill. Ms. Hardy currently lives in Greensboro but continues to visit Washington, D.C., frequently.
      In this oral history interview, Sarah Ann Hardy, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from Randleman, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She discusses her upbringing in Randleman, moving to D.C. in 1966 at age 19, her life in the city and her career working for the federal government, and her return to North Carolina after her retirement in 2008. She also discusses the riots of 1968, the Trump presidency and the contemporary political climate, and the effects of rising property values on people's ability to buy a home.
  - Sub-series 2: Indexes, 2017
    - Herbert Freeman index, 2018-01-04; rwhc_ohp_2017_005_ind.pdf; Freeman, Herbert, 1941-; Okbagabir, Hadnet
    - Jettie Brown index, 2017-12-24; rwhc_ohp_2017_004_ind.pdf; Brown, Jettie M., 1930-
    - Jimmie Suggs index, 2017-12-11; Suggs, Jimmie, 1952-; Woods-Arthur, Maya
    - Reverend Dr. Isaac Fox index, 2017-12-19; Fox, Isaac A.; Messina-Fitzgerald, Clare
      In this oral history interview, the Reverend Dr. Isaac Fox, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Nashville, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. He recalls his upbringing and education in Nashville, his move to D.C. in 1953, and his experiences serving in the U.S. Military. Rev. Fox also discusses his varied educational experiences and his lifelong dedication to education
    - Sarah Ann Hardy index, 2017-12-26; Hardy, Sarah Ann, 1947-; Wilson, Ramani
  - Sub-series 3: Transcripts, 2017
    - Herbert Freeman transcript, 2018-01-04; rwhc_ohp_2017_005_tra.pdf; Freeman, Herbert, 1941-; Okbagabir, Hadnet
    - Jettie Brown transcript, 2017-12-24; rwhc_ohp_2017_004_tra.pdf; Brown, Jettie M., 1930-
    - Jimmie Suggs transcrip, 2017-12-11; Suggs, Jimmie, 1952-; Woods-Arthur, Maya
    - Reverend Dr. Isaac Fox transcript, 2017-12-19; Fox, Isaac A.; Messina-Fitzgerald, Clare
    - Sarah Ann Hardy transcript, 2017-12-26; Hardy, Sarah Ann, 1947-; Wilson, Ramani
- Series 5: 2018-2019 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - Edith Crutchfield interview, 2018-12-14; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Ramos-Bracho, Isabella
      Edith Crutchfield was born on August 28th, 1936, in Culpeper, Virginia. Though Culpeper was segregated, she grew up across the street from a medical professional building, which housed white residents. Ms. Crutchfield remarks that though Culpeper was segregated, this was more integration than she experienced living in D.C. due to housing segregation in the city. Ms. Crutchfield came to the District in 1953 at age sixteen and moved in with her oldest sister and brother-in-law. She studied communication at Howard University as well as the University of the District of Columbia and went on to have a career working in libraries. She worked at libraries within the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) before retiring from the public sector in 1995. Ms. Crutchfield then began work in private law firms. She had one daughter who passed away in 2015.
      In this oral history interview, Edith Crutchfield, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Culpeper, Virginia, to Washington, D.C. Mrs. Crutchfield discusses her upbringing in Culpeper, Virginia, moving to D.C. at age sixteen, and the racial and cultural similarities/differences between the District and the Culpeper. She also discusses the current political climate and the regression she has seen in recent years.
    - Eva McLeod interview, 2018-12-07; McLeod, Eva, 1918-; Washington, Kay; Alvarez, Steven
      Eva M. McLeod was born in 1918 in Albany, Georgia. She celebrated her 100th birthday in July of 2018. Graduating high school as valedictorian when she was 15, she went on to what was then Georgia Normal and Agricultural University, now Albany State University, a public HBCU (Historically black colleges and universities). Mrs. McLeod taught for about two years before moving on to a four-year college in Savannah, Georgia, where she met her husband. She and her husband taught for three years in Georgia before he decided to look for work in D.C. At this point she and her husband had three children, and he felt they needed a greater income. After settling in D.C., she found that life was different yet similar in the Black communities, as many people she knew had settled from southern cities. In thinking about moving from Albany to D.C., working and raising her children, caring for her grandchildren and elderly husband before he passed, Mrs. McLeod remarks that, "I've had my hands full all my life."
      In this oral history interview, Eva McLeod, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Albany, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. Mrs. McLeod, now a widow, discusses her upbringing and education in the South, moving to D.C. with her husband in the mid-forties, career with the postal service, and volunteer work to advance equity in D.C. Mrs. McLeod's daughter Kay Washington, also present for the interview, helps answer some questions
    - Jacqueline Hines interview, 2018-12-28; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Ayodeji, Oluwafunmilayo
      Jacqueline Hines was born in Wilson, North Carolina on April 27, 1954. Though she was sixth of her mother's seven children, she grew up with only her mother and younger sister in the home since her older siblings were from her mother's first marriage and had already moved out. At the age of 15 in the summer of 1969, Ms. Hines came to Washington, D.C.; her mother and sister came north to join her that fall. Ms. Hines was the first in her family to have a high school diploma (Ballou High School) and to get a college degree (Bowie State University). She gave birth to her son after finishing at Bowie State in 1977, and, after staying home with him for a time, she began her career as an educator. Her first teaching job was in a correctional facility but she later began working in DC Public Schools (DCPS). Ms. Hines retired from DCPS in August of 2019.
      In this oral history interview, Jacqueline Hines, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Wilson, North Carolina to Washington, D.C. She discusses her upbringing in Wilson, the reasons her family chose to move to D.C., her time at Ballou High School and Bowie State University, and her career as an educator and social worker. She also talks about issues she has faced since coming to Washington and some of the reasons she has never considered returning to North Carolina.
    - James Jackson interview, 2018-12-21; Jackson, James Lyde, 1936-
      James Jackson was born June 10, 1936, in Oates, South Carolina, but he grew up in nearby Hartsville SC. Mr. Jackson's parents were sharecroppers, and he recalls how landowners exploited farmers and often cheated them at settlement. After finishing high school, Mr. Jackson went into business with his brother building homes, but he eventually decided to move to D.C. since he wasn't making enough to support his growing family. He initially came to D.C. in 1962 without his family, since he wanted to find housing suitable for his wife and children before they came north. He lived with his sister at first, but he was able to secure housing through a job as a building manager and had his family joined him soon after. He worked as a union carpenter for a couple years before landing a job with the Department of Corrections as the facilities manager for a prison. Mr. Jackson retired in 1990.
      In this oral history interview, James Lyde Jackson, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his life and experiences moving from Hartsville, South Carolina to Washington, D.C. Mr. Jackson reflects on his upbringing in Hartsville as the son of sharecroppers, his experiences with segregation, and moving to D.C. in search of better opportunities for his family. He also talks about his children and his career working for the Department of Corrections.
      Diaz-Cruz, Saul
    - Joseph Harris interview, 2018-12; Harris, Joseph E., 1929-; Nikolas, Ferreyra